Nicole: Let's have a look at some threats
and how they can be protected against.
Abraham: A DoS or denial of service
attack is where a computer is used
to flood or crash a system due to too
much internet traffic causing them
to slow down and eventually stop.
This attack can be managed by deploying
firewalls at key points in a network
to filter out unwanted traffic.
This means that the potential victim
doesn't receive or respond to them.
Nicole: A DDoS or distributed denial of
service attack involves multiple systems
orchestrating a synchronised attack to
a single target, overloading a server.
These attacks can be seriously
disruptive as the location is difficult
to detect due to the random nature
of the distribution of the attack.
This form of attack uses
malicious network traffic packets.
Modern security technologies have
developed to defend against DoS attack,
but the DDoS is more of an elevated threat
and of greater concern to cyber security
Abraham: Botnet software
A bot is a piece of malware that
infects a computer to carry out the
commands of the attacker remotely.
A botnet is a number of internet connected
devices that are running one or more bots.
The attacker controls the botnet to hijack
networks of computers to carry out scams
and cyberattacks such as data theft,
server crashing and malware distribution.
While botnets can be an attack
in themselves, they can also be
used to execute secondary attacks.
Nicole: A trojan is a type of malware
often disguised as legitimate software.
Users are often tricked into loading
and executing trojans on their systems.
They enable cyber criminals to
spy and steal sensitive data and
gain backdoor access to a system.
A trojan must be executed by the victim to
gain access to the system via a phishing
or social engineering attack by opening
an infected email or clicking on a link.
This type of threat can be prevented by
not clicking on anything unsolicited.
Abraham: Ransomware is malware
that encrypts and holds a
victim’s information for ransom.
They subsequently cannot access files,
databases or applications and the attacker
demands a ransom to provide access.
If a system is infected with ransomware
an appropriate decryption tool
will be needed to regain access.
Antivirus software should be able to
protect systems but also having back
up data will help in the short term.
Nicole: Spyware is a form of malware
that secretly infects a computer to
gather information such as the sites
visited, usernames, passwords, payment
information and email activity.
It runs quietly in the
background monitoring activities.
Spyware can enter your computer
through freeware, software bundles
and phishing and malvertising and
it can also attack smartphones.
If spyware is suspected or to protect
against it a good cybersecurity
program or a robust antivirus software
can be used to clean up the system.
Abraham: Worms are designed to spread from
computer to computer and have the ability
to reproduce themselves to do this.
It operates by inserting itself
into a legitimate programme or
document that supports macros
in order to execute its code.
To do this it can create
unexpected and damaging effects
and corrupt or destroy data.
It can remain dormant until the
device executes its code and
once that is infected it can
infect others in the network.
It can steal passwords, corrupt files and
spam email contacts amongst other things.
Antivirus software protects against
more than viruses and is an older term.
We now tend to refer to it as
antimalware software because it
protects against all types of
malicious software including viruses.